<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="dataDocGuide">
	<title>Guide to AAMA Documentation</title>
	<para><remark>Note that at this point the documentation is in large part a lightly annotated set
			of lists progammatically generated from the output of a set of SPARQL queries, listing
			lexemes (output-. . . .rq[XREF]), morphosyntactic properties and values (output- . . .
			.rq[XREF], and a systematic index of paradigms (output-pdgmlabel-prop-val.rq [XREF].
			Although we hope that this skeletal documentation will be helpful in finding and
			interpreting the data in the archive, it should be obvious what a distance there is
			between it and a morphological monograph or article. We trust that enough bibliography
			has been given to give the user a start on the more or less extensive literature that
			exists on each language.</remark></para>
	<para>Each language documentation will contain the following information:</para>
	<sect1>
		<title>General Information</title>
		<sect2>
			<title>Location-Speakers</title>
			<para> The geographic location, estimated number of speakers, and attested varieties and
				subdialects of the language or language-variety in question. For the Cushitic-Omotic
				area, roughly the Horn of Africa and some adjacent areas in Sudan, Kenya, and
				Tanzania, a very helpful souce, and one usually linked to is the on-line <link
					xlink:href="http://www.ethnologue.org">Ethnologue</link> catalogue, corrected or
				supplemented by other information, where necessary. The family-tree/genetic
				affliliation position assumed in the archive and presented in the systematic
				language index is not always identical with that of Ethnologue. Note that Ethnologue
				does not in principle offer coverage of ancient languages, and that other sources
				will be relied on and cited for those cases. </para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Bibliographic Source</title>
			<para>Generally at this stage, the data from each language is taken from a single
				monographic source, whose reference is given in this section. </para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Paradigm Lexemes</title>
		<para> Lemma and gloss of the lexical items which are used in the verbal paradigms.Where
			possible a single paradigm lexeme is used for each unique collection of morphosyntactic
			properties, including inflectional class. On occasion, the fragmentary nature of the
			documentation does not allow this. This is especially the case for dead languages, and
			for poorly or no longer attested varieties of living languages.</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Morphosyntactic Properties</title>
		<para>
			<remark>To be added: more detail about unevenness of coverage, reason for not choosing
				noun paradigms; rationale for what gets included; somewhat arbitrary boundary
				between phonological and morphophonemic/morphological alternation -- especially in
				area of inflection classes [what is considered a phonological alternation in one
				source is a inflection class in another]. Notion of base paradigm -- the paradigms
				which were actually entered into the data-base; these must always be available in
				txt or xml form [HAVE TO DECIDE WHICH ONE IS NORMATIVE!].</remark>
		</para>
		<para>This section of each language's data documentation contains a list of the
			morphosyntactic properties and their values used in the paradigms of the language in
			question. These are given in separate sections for the major part-of-speech paradigm
			sets, the pronominal and the varbal. In addition, a separate section is given for
			Person-Number-Gender (PNG) properties, which occupy a unique overlapping position
			between pronoun (often as defining properties) and verb (as the principal
			subject-agreement properties throughout the macro-family). <remark>Note that in many
				cases this section contains only an unannotated list of the paradigm properties (=
				row/col headings), each with a list of its values. As documentation proceeds on a
				language-by-language basis, theexplanation of the morphological paradigm dimensions
				with become (asymptotically) more complete.</remark>
		</para>
		<para> Where necessary a word of explanation or an illustrative gloss will be given for
			properties or values whose sense is not immediately clear; this is a work in progress,
			and the amount of explanation or glossing will differ from language to language and from
			one release to another. In this context however it cannot be overemphasized that a set
			of labeled paradigms is not the morphology of a language but a tool for the exploration
			of that morphology, and that the present archive is not a comparative grammar of
			Cushitic-Omotic (or Afroasiatic), but a presentation of an important part of the data
			that such a grammar (or set of grammars) must account for -- and as well an implicit
			invitation to collect and organize whatever additional material might be necessary to
			make such a grammar possible. The labels and explanatory glosses given in the
			documentation and paradigm notes will hopefully give the user an idea, perhaps more or
			less precise according to his or her background, of the morphosyntactic properties and
			values involved in the morphology of a given language. But they are no substitute for
			the fuller presentation which will be found in each case in the source monograph, book
			or article.</para>
		<para>Property-value associations will differ in detail from language to language. But there
			is a great similarity in their inventory across the archive, and a typical documentation
			page will usually approximate the following outline, which contains some property-values
			associations and comments on them which apply virtually across the whole range of
			Cushitic-Omotic languages, and which will be linked to from individual language data
			documentations.</para>
		<itemizedlist xml:id="cushOmPNG">
			<title>Cushitic-Omotic PNG Properties</title>
			<listitem>
				<para xml:id="cushOmoticPNG">PNG includes, almost universally in Cushitic Omotic,
					the following properties and values: <itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para>number</para>
							<orderedlist>
								<listitem>
									<para>singular <abbrev>sg</abbrev></para>
								</listitem>
								<listitem>
									<para>plural <abbrev>pl</abbrev></para>
								</listitem>
							</orderedlist>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>person</para>
							<orderedlist>
								<listitem>
									<para>first <abbrev>p1</abbrev></para>
								</listitem>
								<listitem>
									<para>second <abbrev>p2</abbrev></para>
								</listitem>
								<listitem>
									<para>thirs <abbrev>p3</abbrev></para>
								</listitem>
							</orderedlist>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>gender</para>
							<orderedlist>
								<listitem>
									<para>masculine <abbrev>m</abbrev></para>
								</listitem>
								<listitem>
									<para>feminine <abbrev>f</abbrev></para>
								</listitem>
							</orderedlist>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</para>
				<para>It should be noted that not all combinations of number, person, and gender
					acutally occur, and in fact, with a few notable exceptions (e.g., Beja) the
					prevailing PNG pattern in Cushitic and Omotic is: <informaltable>
						<thead>
							<tr>
								<td>number</td>
								<td>person</td>
								<td>gender</td>
							</tr>
						</thead>
						<tbody>
							<tr>
								<td>sg</td>
								<td>p1</td>
								<td>"⊤"</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>sg</td>
								<td>p2</td>
								<td>"⊤"</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>sg</td>
								<td>p3</td>
								<td>m</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>sg</td>
								<td>p3</td>
								<td>f</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>pl</td>
								<td>p1</td>
								<td>"⊤"</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>pl</td>
								<td>p2</td>
								<td>"⊤"</td>
							</tr>
							<tr>
								<td>pl</td>
								<td>p3</td>
								<td>"⊤"</td>
							</tr>
						</tbody>
					</informaltable> I.e., where gender is distinguished only in the third-person
					singular. This pattern is so pervasive in Cushitic and Omotic that it will be
					referred to in the individual language documentation simply as the %-link
					linkend="cushOmPNG"-% Cushitic-Omotic PNG Pattern%-/link-%. PNG details will be
					given only when a language departs from this pattern. Note the symbol "⊤"
					("down-tack", Unicode x22A4, logical "null:), which will be used in this archive
					for linguistic neutralization, in this case, of the gender distinction; i.e.,
					sg-p1, sg-p2, and pl can be used in both masculine and feminine agreement
					contexts. For linguistic "null" the correlated symbol "⊥" (up-tack, Unicode
					x22A5) will be used.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<itemizedlist>
			<title>Pronoun Properties</title>
			<listitem>
				<para>case: The pronominal (and nominal) case system in most Cushitic(-Omotic)
					languages is of the "marked nominative (or subject)" type, wherein the subject
					of a clause is marked with a special suffix, as opposed to an unmarked "base (or
					absolutive)", which serves as citation form, direct object, and form to which
					oblique case postpositions are suffixed. There is often some way of expressing a
					possessive/genitive case, either by suffix or final vowel lengthening. As with
					PNG, this case pattern will be referred in in individual language documentation
					simply as the %-link linkend="cushOmCase"-% Cushitic-Omotic Case
					Pattern%-/link-%.</para>
				<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>base ~ absolutive</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>subject ~ nominative</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>possessive ~ genitive</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>oblique: when given, will be with a list of oblique case postpositions
							(usually NP-final</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>type: This will be a list of the pronoun types attested in the various
					paradigms</para>

				<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>independent</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>possessiveSuffix</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>demonstrative</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>etc.</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<itemizedlist>
			<title>Verb Selector Properties: "Verb Selector" is a pre-verbal cliltic, or clitic
				chain which takes up, sometimes in a morphologically redundant fashion, sometimes
				not, a number of properties of the following verb. These properties differ from
				language to language, but often incllude pronominal subject markings, object
				parkings, and reference to verbal tense, aspect, and mood properties. The category,
				which is perhaps an areal one (cf. Bantu, from which the term derives), is limited
				(Oromo) or non-existent in more northerly Cushitic languages, fairly common in
				Omo-Tana, and highly developed in Southern Cushitic. Categories such as the
				following are common:</title>
			<listitem>
				<para>selProClass</para>
				<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>preVerbSel_SubjMarkers</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>preVerbSelSubjMarkers</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>definite</para>
				<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>definite</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>indefinite</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>mood</para>
				<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>indicative</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>non-indicative</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<itemizedlist>
			<title>Verb Properties</title>
			<listitem>
				<para>polarity: For the most part "affirmative" vs. "negative", although some
					variations and elaborations occur. It should be noted that few Cushitic-Omotic
					languages have negative forms of the simple additive type, whereby a verb is
					rendered negative by simple placement of a negative word, clitic, or affix next
					to the affirmative form of the verb. Negative forms, although they usually
					involve some negative formative, frequently have a distinct morphology,
					frequently with fewer tam or PNG distinctions than the affirmative. These
					restrictions for an individual language will usually be summarized in "Verb
					Properties" section, with details, if necessary, either under the polarity or
					the tense property sections.</para>
				<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>affirmative</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>negative</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>theme: The theme or derived stem sections usually involve the following
					categories, and in most languages, combinations of these are possible:
					causative+causative (double causative) is very frequent, as are
					middle+causative, passive+causative, and causative+passive. Grammars differ
					widely in the extent to which all possible combinations are documented, and in
					some languages there are distinct differences among dialects, varieties, and
					even idiolects as to the acceptability of various theme combinations</para>
				<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>base: Usually unmarked.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>causative: very frequently marked with prefix or suffix -s- (xref::
							see below on prefixing and suffixing inflectional class)</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>middle/benefactive: often with prefix or suffix dental, voiced,
							voiceless, or retroflex (xref:: see below on prefixing and suffixing
							inflectional class)</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>passive: very frequently marked with prefix or suffix -m- (xref:: see
							below on prefixing and suffixing inflectional class)</para>
					</listitem>

				</orderedlist>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>composition: A subdistinction of %-link linkend="tam"-%
					Tense-Aspect-Mode%-/link-%</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>simple</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>compound</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>tam: Tense-Aspect-Mode. </para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>simple: Most Cushitic-Omotic languages have simple (lexical verb only)
							inflectional paradigms corresponding to the following categories,
							sometimes with a complementary distribution between the jussive (with no
							second person) and the imperative (second person only). </para>
						<orderedlist>
							<listitem>
								<para>present</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>past</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>jussive</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>imperative</para>
							</listitem>
						</orderedlist>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>compound: Many, and perhaps most, Cushitic-Omotic lanuages have
							compound (lexical verb plus one or more peripheral auxiliary or clitic
							elements), yielding a much more detailed inventory of tense, aspect, and
							modal distinctions. The treatment of these varies widely in the archive
							sources. Some investigators give them perfunctory treatment, or even
							ignore them completely. Others furnish long series of compound
							paradigms, to a point where it becomes difficult to see where Verb+Aux
							leaves off and regular Verb+Complement constructions start -- a
							notorious problem in any case in the debate over the boundary between
							morphology and syntax. In this archive we will simply reproduce the
							distinctions made in the source document. Since many of these
							distinctions are (morpho-)syntactically and semantically quite complex,
							in addition to the name, in the annotation I will simply give a
							translational paraphrase, and refer the user to the original source for
							more complete discussion. Typical compound paradigm categories
							are:</para>
						<orderedlist>
							<listitem>
								<para>perfect </para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>future </para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>progressive </para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>conditional</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>etc. </para>
							</listitem>
						</orderedlist>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>inflectionClass: as in all languages, phonological and grammaticization
					processes conspire to create more or less marked morphophonemic differences in
					the verbal inflections of different sets of verbs. </para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>affixationClass: Cross-cutting normal inflectional class in some
							branches of Cushitic (Beja and Omo-Tana, perhaps also Agaw) is an
							archaic Afroasiatic distinction between prefix conjugations (where the
							PNG subject markers are at least partially prefixed, and tam
							distinctions can be marked by internal vowel change) and suffix
							conjugations (where PNG subject markers are totally suffixed, and the
							verb base is invariant). It should be noted that , as opposed to
							Semitic, where this formal distinction corresponds to a tense-aspect
							distinction (past/non-past, perfective/imperfective) in all verbs, in
							the Cushitic languages which preserve it, this distinction is lexical,
							and a given verb-base is conjugated completely either in the prefix or
							the suffix pattern. Note further that in all Cushitic languages the
							productive pattern is the suffix-conjugation: only Beja and Saho-Afar
							have large numbers of prefix-conjugated verbs, and in the Omo-Tana
							languages the prefix-conjugated class is limited to a small inventory of
							at most a couple dozen high-frequency lexical items</para>
						<itemizedlist>
							<listitem>
								<para>prefixConjugation</para>
								<orderedlist>
									<listitem>
										<para>sub-class1 </para>
									</listitem>
									<listitem>
										<para>sub-class2 </para>
									</listitem>
									<listitem>
										<para>etc. </para>
									</listitem>
									<listitem>
										<para>etc. </para>
									</listitem>
								</orderedlist>

							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>suffixConjugation</para>
								<orderedlist>
									<listitem>
										<para>sub-class1 </para>
									</listitem>
									<listitem>
										<para>sub-class2 </para>
									</listitem>
									<listitem>
										<para>etc. </para>
									</listitem>
									<listitem>
										<para>etc. </para>
									</listitem>
								</orderedlist>

							</listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>special: almost every language has one or more infledctionally exceptional
					class of verbs, frequently involving the expression of "to be" in one or more of
					its senses and "to have"</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para> </para>
						<orderedlist>
							<listitem>
								<para> </para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para> </para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para> </para>
							</listitem>
						</orderedlist>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>nonFinite</para>
				<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>infinitive</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para> </para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para> </para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Attested Archive Paradigms</title>
		<para>The following table indicates the feature-value combinations actually documented in
			the original archive base paradigms. For the moment these are taken from a paradigm
			index compiled on an earlier format or terminology that are actually represented by the
			normative LANG-pdgms.xml document. An update is in process.. Except where noted, all
			finite tam-forms occur with all PNG combinations.Clicking on the paradigmLabel will
			yield a display of the paradigm in question [either by link to hard-coded term cluster,
			or canned SPARQL query]. The following table outline is typical. </para>
		<table>
			<caption>Documented Default Verbal Paradigms</caption>
			<thead>
				<tr>
					<th>paradigmLabel</th>
					<th>paradigmLex</th>
					<th>theme</th>
					<th>clauseType</th>
					<th>polarity</th>
					<th>tam</th>
					<th>inflectionType</th>
					<th>note</th>
				</tr>
			</thead>
			<tbody>
				<tr>
					<td> </td>
					<td> </td>
					<td> </td>
					<td> </td>
					<td> </td>
					<td> </td>
					<td> </td>
					<td> </td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td> </td>
					<td> </td>
					<td> </td>
					<td> </td>
					<td> </td>
					<td> </td>
					<td> </td>
					<td> </td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td> </td>
					<td> </td>
					<td> </td>
					<td> </td>
					<td> </td>
					<td> </td>
					<td> </td>
					<td> </td>
				</tr>
			</tbody>

		</table>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Phonological Inventory</title>
		<para>Eventually a phonological chart will be provided for each language.</para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
