<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="projIntro">
	<title>The AAMA Project</title>
	<section>
		<title>Project Overview</title>
		<para> The Afroasiatic Morphological Archive is an on-going project with two goals: <orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>To assemble for exploration/investigation [through this tool?] a
						relatively comprehensive repertory of morphological paradigms -- in this
						case a large, but by no means complete, selection of Cushitic and Omotic
						verbal and pronominal paradigms, as they are documented in the best, most
						recent monographic treatments. To facilitate comparative exploration of
						paradigmatic material, in this initial release a small sample, gradually to
						be expanded, of other Afroasiatic is also included. </para>
					<para>It goes without saying that a set of paradigms does not constitute a
						morphology, but rather data for, or illustrations of, a language's
						morphology (in traditional grammars such a set usually constitutes an
						appendix or supplement to the actualy grammar) -- and there is actually a
						lively current debate about the theoretical status of such data-structures.
						However, the introduction to each language will contain a list of the
						morphosyntactic categories and values involved in the paradigms, with
						hopefully enough brief glosses and explanatory notes to give the interested
						by non-expert user an idea of what is going on [but always with the implicit
						injunction to consult the source monograph!]. An explanation of the
						organization and scope of the morphological data is contained in %-xref-%
						Part One of the documentation. </para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>To provide a tool for exploring and manipulating a database of
						morphological paradigms: specifically for the formation, transformation,
						combination, and comparison of morphological paradigmatic displays from a
						set of input morphological data, itself generally paradigmatic in form, with
						the goal of facilitating comparative insight into the interplay of
						morphological processes and morphosyntactic categories and values within and
						between between languages. An introduction to this aspect of the archive is
						contained in %-xref-% Part Two of the documentation</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para> To provide a framework for collaborative sharing of morphological
						material: In the first instance, Cushitic-Omotic and general Afroasiatic,
						but potentially also from other families as well. An introduction to this
						aspect of the archive is contained in %-xref-% Part Three of the
						documentation</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>The Morphological Paradigm</title>
		<para xml:id="morphPdgm"> The working definition of morphological paradigm as used in the project: A large part
			of the morphology of a language (or, by extension, of a group of languages) is
			traditionally captured in paradigms -- tables of linguistic units whose shape varies
			systematically in accordance with different combinations of the values (e.g.,
			singular/plural, first/second/third, masculine/feminine, past/present) of a set of
			properties (e.g., "number", "person", "gender", "tense"). In the default case, the units
			in question are words, and the paradigms show the set of possible forms which can be
			taken by an exemplary lexical item (here the "paradigm lexeme"). But paradigms can also
			be parts of words (affixes, clitics, vowel patterns, tone patterns), or words plus
			adjuncts (word+clitic, word+auxiliary ). Note that the criteria for assigning these
			latter compound constructions to morphology vs. syntax in the archive sources can vary
			significantly from one investigator to another, and that the notion of paradigm can also
			be used for data which is unambiguously semantic, syntactic, or phonological. </para>
		<para>A set of paradigms for a single language is more or less complete to the extent that
			the information it contains is sufficient for learning, illustrating, or (analogically)
			inducing the inflectional morphology of the languge in question. Bi- or multi-lingual
			paradigms are used to illustrate systematic similarities and differences between related
			languages or varieties of languages, and are widely used as a tool in historical or
			typological investigations. Whatever the theoretical or psychological status of the
			paradigm (a range of contemporary views can be found in some recent collections such as
			Bachrach and Nevins 2008, and Blevins and Blevins 2009), the paradigm is indisputably an
			indispensible tool in the collection, organization, comparison, learning, and exposition
			of inflectional language data. Working with data of this kind unavoidably implies at
			some level working with paradigms </para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Paradigm Formation and Manipulation</title>
		<para>[Rationale for formulating and manipulating mono- and pluri-lingual paradigms]</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>A Collaborative Archive</title>
		<para>In addition, the archive is conceived of as an on-going and collaborative effort. We
			hope that eventually individuals/users with the relevant expertise will contribute new
			material from other areas of Afroasiatic and from Cushitic and Omotic languages,
			dialects, and varieties not covered here, and most importantly provide continuous
			correction and comment on data already contained in the archive (wiki-grammar). %-xref-%
			Part Three of the documentation contains the information relevant to the formatting and
			submission of extensions to the archive.</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
